■ b.jelfs@bham.ac.uk

beteje.github.io
in bethjelfs

beteje

Beth Jelfs

My research focusses on adaptive signal processing especially statistical signal processing and signal characterisation. At the core of all my research is the belief that understanding more about the nature of signal generation mechanisms can aid and inform our choice of machine learning algorithms. I have worked on the theoretical foundations of this approach and have applied my work to a wide range of problems particularly with reference to biomedical and neural applications.

Education

PhD Electrical & Electronic Engineering

April 2010

Imperial College London, UK

Thesis: Collaborative Adaptive Filtering for Machine Learning Awarded Engineering & Physical Sciences Research Council

Doctoral Training Award

MEng Electronic & Software Engineering

July 2005

UK

University of Leicester, UK

1st Class Honours

Awarded British Computer Society's prize for best graduating student

Research Experience

Assistant Professor in Signal Processing & Data Analysis

April 2022 - Present

Dept. Electronic, Electrical & Systems Engineering, University of Birmingham,

My research focuses on adaptive signal processing algorithms for signal characterisation and machine learning. Current projects include:

- Integration of machine learning with novel biomarkers for prostate cancer diagnosis & prognosis;
- Study of neural responses during stroke rehabilitation & the effects of virtual reality;
- Brain connectivity changes after cochlear implant.

Lecturer (Assistant Professor)
March 2021 – March 2022

Vice-Chancellor's Research Fellow

March 2017 – March 2021 School of Engineering, RMIT University, Australia Research projects involved development of signal processing algorithms for a variety of applications including:

- Development of time-varying delay estimation algorithms;
- Image processing & machine learning for tracking cell/tissue responses;
- Path-prediction for high-altitude balloons.

Research Fellow
June 2015 – October 2016
Postdoctoral Fellow

August 2013 – May 2015

Dept. Electronic Engineering, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Coordinated project "Fingers Working in Coordination: Hierarchy of EEG, EMG and Kinematics" funded by the Hong Kong Research Grant Council.

Developed a project as part of the Centre for Biosystems, Neuroscience, and Nanotechnology on computational methods for neural synchronization & information transfer.

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Dept. Medical Physics & Bioengineering, University College London, UK June 2011 – June 2013 Responsible for designing the signal processing aspects of project "Integrating monitoring & modelling for real time tracking of cerebral circulation & metabolism" funded by Wellcome Trust Project Grant.

Postdoctoral Research Assistant

Dept. Chemistry & Dept. Physics, University of Oxford, UK June 2010 – June 2011 Developed statistical signal processing techniques to study nanopore technology and the accuracy of classification for DNA sequencing.

Grants & Awards

Collaborative Research Agreement

University of South Australia & Trinity
College Dublin
2022–Ongoing

Goal: Automated prostate cancer diagnosis and prognosis.

Role: Development of image processing and machine learning

biomarker developed by collaborators.

Ideation Challenge

SmartSat Cooperative Research Centre 2020

Goal: Development of a vision based attitude estimation system for high altitude platforms.

software to be licensed for use in conjunction with a tissue

Role: Successfully lead a project to rapidly conceive and produce a minimum viable product. This has been invited to be developed into a more complete system in a subsequent project.

Project for the Defence Artificial Intelligence Centre

Trusted Autonomous Systems Defence Cooperative Research Centre **Goal:** Performance assessment for a self-organising low-cost, high altitude balloon constellation for persistent surveillance and communications.

Role: Development of a simulation platform to allow assessment of performance based on real and simulated data.

Maxwell Eagle Endowment Award

RMIT University 2020

2020-2021

Goal: Using machine-based learning to develop prognostics of CAR T cell outcomes in older patients.

Role: Developing image processing and predictive machine learning algorithms.

Capability Development Fund

RMIT University 2019

Goal: High throughput platform for tracking cellular response. **Role:** Creating efficient image processing algorithms for development of high volume machine learning architecture.

Global Connections Fund Bridging Grant

Australian Academy of Technology Sciences and Engineering

Goal: Development of a wireless portable device to monitor muscle fatigue in collaboration with PLUX Wireless Biosignals a Portuguese SME.

Role: Successfully designed new algorithms to assess muscle status in real time.

Scheme for Teaching and Learning Research

RMIT University 2017

2017-2018

Goal: Developing the framework for problem based learning workshop style education.

Role: Design of framework.

Vice-Chancellor's Research Fellowship

RMIT University 2017–2021

Goal: To investigate the use of time-varying algorithms in the assessment of biomedical data for machine learning applications. **Role:** Sole investigator, project design, management and dissemination of results.

Research Exchange Project

BayChina 2015

2010

2007

Collaboration with Neuroscientific Theory Group at TU München.

Best Student Paper Award

International Symposium on Neural Networks For paper "Modelling of Brain Consciousness based on Collaborative Adaptive Filters".

Academic Research Collaboration Project

Collaboration with TU München and the Max-Planck-Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization.

British Council and DAAD

International Travel GrantRoyal Academy of Engineering

Awarded to attend IEEE International Conference on Acoustics Speech and Signal Processing.

Teaching Experience

Lecturer, Computer and Network Security

RMIT University 2021

Delivery & redesign of teaching materials for the computer security aspects of a technical elective for 4th year undergraduate and taught masters with $\sim\!50$ students.

Tutor, Engineering Computing

RMIT University 2021

Delivering C++ tutorials as part of a core 2nd year undergraduate engineering course with $\sim\!\!200$ students.

Lecturer, Signals & Systems ${\bf 1}$

RMIT University 2019–2020

Offshore course taught at School for Higher and Professional Education, Vocational Training Council, Hong Kong.

Course Coordinator, Biomedical Signal Analysis

RMIT University 2018–2021

Design and delivery of a core 3rd year undergraduate course in biomedical engineering and technical elective for electronic engineering with ${\sim}50$ students.

Guest Lecturer, Brain Machine Interface: Technology, Culture, and Society

Lecturing on BMI Technology & Neural Computation for a university elective with $\sim\!\!200$ students.

City University of Hong Kong 2014–2015

International Transition Team Graduate Teaching Assistant

City University of Hong Kong 2013–2015

Providing English language support including student tutorials, proofreading of academic papers & preparation of teaching materials.

Tutor, Communications I

Imperial College London 2006–2008

Teaching study groups of $\sim \!\! 30$ students for a core 1st year undergraduate course in electronic engineering.

Service to Field

Associate Editor

Encyclopedia BRAIN

Responsible for sourcing and reviewing content on signal & image processing

2021

Steering Committee Member SmartSat Cooperative Research Centre 2020–2022 Al4Space Research Network: to progress research and development in Al applied to space systems and technologies.

Special Session Organiser

APSIPA Annual Summit & Conference

Multidimensional Biomedical Signal and Image Processing.

2020

Special Session Organiser Emerging Technologies for Healthcare.

APSIPA Annual Summit & Conference 2018

Vice-Chancellor's Fellows Advisory
Group

Liasing with Research & Innovation Office to provide improved procedures for fellows.

RMIT University 2017–2022

Organising events to promote the fellows' research and collaboration between fellows.

Organising committee

"enGENEious" conference, Oxford, UK 2012

Student & Post-doc lead conference on microbial engineering.

Public Engagement & Invited Talks

Research Seminar

Bionics Institute, Australia 2021

Talk on surrogate data and what to do when we don't know the ground truth.

Engaging for Impact

RMIT University, Australia 2020

Talk on Tissue Image Processing for Innovation in Healthcare with Precision Medicine session.

Biomedical Engineering Dept.

Shantou University China

Shantou University, China 2019

Invited lecture series on biomedical signal processing.

Bioinformatics Network Symposium

RMIT University, Australia 2019

Talk on Machine Learning for High Throughput Cell Imaging.

Pint of Science

Event manager for science festival for the general public.

London, UK 2013

UCL Outreach

Lead demonstrations and talks with school children for events including:

University College London, UK

2011-2013

- Medical Physics Masterclass;

- Women in Engineering Taster Day;

- University Challenge Event.

Doctoral Training Centre

University of Oxford, UK 2011

Talk on DNA Nanopore Sequencing.

Faculty of Computer Science

University of Applied Sciences Schmalkalden, Germany 2008

Talk on Signal Modality Characterisation Using Collaborative Adaptive Filters.

Professional Associations

Asia-Pacific Signal & Information

Processing Association (APSIPA) 2018-present

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers 2006-present

Member

- Chair Biomedical Signal Processing & Systems Technical Committee

Member

- Member of Women in Signal Processing Empowerment, Awareness and Visibility Subcommittee
- Affiliate member of Bio Imaging and Signal Processing Technical Committee
- Member of Signal Processing Society
- Member of Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society